<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>My Blog</title><link href="/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="/feeds/all.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>/</id><updated>2016-01-09T10:20:00+05:30</updated><entry><title>How to protect your privacy online</title><link href="/online-privacy.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2016-01-09T10:20:00+05:30</published><author><name>Lucifer</name></author><id>tag:,2016-01-09:online-privacy.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="http://blog.mozillaindia.org/wp-content/uploads/2016/01/Privacy-Month-cover.png"  width="800" height="300" alt="CMozilla Privacy Month"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First of all let me start by explaining the meaning of the word "Privacy".&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Privacy(n):A state in which one is not observed or disturbed by other people.(or) The state of being free from public attention.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All of us on the internet like to browse and look for interesting content which are available online.
But what most of us don't know is that alot of our information is shared.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;What is Data Privacy?&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Data privacy, also called information privacy, is the aspect of information technology (IT) that deals with the ability an organization or individual has to determine what data in a computer system can be shared with third parties.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;How does our data being shared affect us ?&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This might sound like a silly question at first,but when you think about it, it is the most important question you must be asking. What is being done with our data? Why does it benefit other websites for having our information?. For people who say "I'm just a normal guy/girl nothing can be done with having my information. You are wrong. This is like saying I'll give anyone access into my house and my personal space because I'm normal. All of us should exercise our right to Privacy online and offline.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Edward Snowden's Quote" src="https://40.media.tumblr.com/b45e86371a4d6754231c41175f8a47a2/tumblr_nznaohqBGz1rg3ql7o1_500.jpg" /&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So now to the next topic,How do I protect my data and prevent it from being shared online,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here are some steps you can follow to prevent your data from being shared online.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Note: These are not in any particular order whatsoever.All of them are important to protect your privacy online&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Step 1:Don't Share your location online.&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yes that includes sharing your location in Facebook and other social sites as well. Sharing your location online is the best way to lose your privacy. Sharing your location let's others know where you hangout alot and makes your private hangouts which must be kept private vulnerable.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Step 2:Always read the terms and conditions.&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That's right.Remember the long paragraph's of texts which you don't read before you click "I Accept" ? Read them. I know it is tiring and boring but trust me it is worth the effort. You should know what the software you install does and what you shouldn't do to violate it. A lot of softwares collect data about you. Hence you should always check why they collect data and what are the reasons for them to collect the data.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Step 3:No need to share everything on Social Media&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Status updates and posting your thoughts are cool but there is no reason to share everything on Social Media,Remember to set the exact privacy settings on each post and to not share stuff which is personal and uneccessary to be shared online.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Step 4:Don't save passwords&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is strongly adviced not to store passwords online since it is vulnerable to attacks and threats. Also change your passwords often.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Step 5:Check your apps' permissions:&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Every app you install in your smartphone requires permissions.Remember that photo collage which required you to allow location services?It is tracking you. Unwantedly and Unknowningly you share your information online.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Step 6:Activate Track Protection&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Firefox now allows you to turn on Tracking Protection and stop all the other Third Party cookeis from gathering informatiobn about you. It is also available in other browsers like chrome. But I personally prefer and suggest Firefox.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now that we've seen about how to protect our privacy,Here are some tools you can you to observe and safeguard it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Tools:&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This site contains a lot of cool tools to protect your privacy! Link: &lt;a href="https://www.privacytools.io/"&gt;Privacy Tools&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Firefox Lightbeam : Create a “Wizard of Oz” moment by pulling back the curtain to see who’s watching you on the Web. Turn on Mozilla’s Lightbeam tool, visit a handful of websites to see who’s tracking you, and then learn how to fight back. You’ll never look at the Web the same way again!.&lt;a href="https://webmaker.org/en-US/private-eye"&gt;Firefox Lightbeam&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally here are some tips by Mozilla on Privacy Protection: &lt;a href="https://www.mozilla.org/en-US/privacy/tips/"&gt;Get smart on Privacy&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="Mozilla"></category><category term="firefox"></category><category term="fsa"></category><category term="Privacy Month"></category></entry><entry><title>Track protection in Firefox</title><link href="/track-protection-firefox.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2015-11-17T10:20:00+05:30</published><author><name>Lucifer</name></author><id>tag:,2015-11-17:track-protection-firefox.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Track Protection" src="http://o.aolcdn.com/hss/storage/midas/f0d730ba55898a63e749d04575e25b15/202479867/firefox-private-browsing.jpg" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Hello World,&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This blog of mine is about the new tracking protection feature in the Mozilla Firefox Browser version 42 and above.Let me cover what is tracking first and then go into how Firefox prevents this.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;What is Tracking ?&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Basically what tracking is is when you are browsing through sites and think you are are browsing safely,Third party ads in those site track your movements online which are known as digital footprints.These footprints allow you to be tracked throughout the web.
for a better pictorial representation check:&lt;a href="https://www.abine.com/what-is-online-tracking/"&gt;What is Online Tracking&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;What are Cookies?&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Cookies are small encrypted document.It contains helpful information about you and your preferences.It helps the websites to store your preferences the first time you visit and have the same preferences the next time you visit without you having to set it again.
As cookies gradually grew the size limitation of it was a problem at first,later they found a way to store unlimited information about you by making a unique id for you in your cookie and storing the information in their own servers.
This led to the possibility of you being tracked and traced online.
for a in depth video about cookies check: &lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=I01XMRo2ESg"&gt;What is a Cookie?&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Firefox Tracking Protection:&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Basically what Firefox Tracking Protection allows you to do is,It Blocks all the ads and other sources in a site which can potentially track you online.thereby giving you total anonymity and makes you feel safe and secure online.
It also gives you the freedom to change which all sites can track you and which all can't.Thereby giving the user full control over his/her online experience.
Wanna try the latest version of Firefox:&lt;a href="https://www.mozilla.org/en-US/firefox/new/"&gt;Download Firefox&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="Mozilla"></category><category term="firefox"></category><category term="fsa"></category><category term="Privacy Month"></category></entry><entry><title>My First Experience as a Firefox Student Ambassador</title><link href="/first-experience-as-a-fsa.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2015-11-16T10:20:00+05:30</published><author><name>Lucifer</name></author><id>tag:,2015-11-16:first-experience-as-a-fsa.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Hello World,Let me start this blog by saying what a wonderful thing it has been for me to know about the Firefox student ambassador program.I first went to the Firefox Trichy meetup on July.The Meetup was at Dominoes,Trichy.It was the first time I met Vigneshwar and a lot of other cool people. Vigneshwer pointed out the roles of a FSA and what we should do in order to help others become aware of Firefox and Open Source.Since then I've been very much interested in learning how the Foundation of coding works and how a program is developed from ground up.It was a once in a lifetime opportunity for me and I thank all those who helped me to get to this.I've solely decided to do everything i can to teach as many people as I can about the Open web and its uses.I have since then been an active contributor for Mozilla Location Services and Quality Assurance.This is the start of my  Journey as a Firefox Student Ambassador and there are lots more to come.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="Mozilla"></category><category term="firefox"></category><category term="fsa"></category></entry><entry><title>MozCoffee Trichy Meetup</title><link href="/mozcoffee-trichy-meetup.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2015-10-22T10:20:00+05:30</published><author><name>Lucifer</name></author><id>tag:,2015-10-22:mozcoffee-trichy-meetup.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;I'm so excited,Finally met Abhiram after three months.He is one of the few people I know who is down to Earth and supports a new FSA with even the most basic of things.So before we go into what happened in the meeting I'd like to let you guys know what I've done in these three months as a Firefox Student Ambassador.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I was told that Mozilla Location Services,was the hot topic during that duration.One of the ways to contribtue was to use the Mozilla stumbler app and scan for new cells using the Wifi on our android phones.Here's the catch,I didn't have a so called "Android" phone when this was happening,and no I didn't have one of those Nokia 1100's as well. I was stuck with one of those windows phones which had apps which were last updated during the STONE AGE.I felt hopeless when I wasn't able to stumble.Also the second problem was as I pointed out I wasn't able to move to Telegram since the app they had was last updated long ago.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I was still fairly new to the community and had no experience about github and all those other stuff.All I knew was the common C and C++ from School,but was good enough to write my own programs.This was the time I decided to explore the community and that's how I got to know Abhiram.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lucky for me he had a friend's wedding here at Trichy so he decided to keep a meetup at NIT-Trichy's Cafe Coffee Day in the Evening after the wedding day.So as usual my eagerness got the better of me and I started procrastinating and started overimagining about how the meetup is gonna be what is going to happen and what I'd end up doing also those kind of stuff.So I had to slowly move back to normalcy and started getting ready to go to the meetup.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As I live fairly near NIT it was like a 10 minute bus travel for me to reach there,(Grandparents won't let me drive the bike as they are afraid something would happen to me eventhough I'm 19).After boarding the bus to my surprise my little friend subbu was travelling on the same bus.So as usual we started arguing on random stuff and reached NIT.
We had to wait an agonizing 30 minutes until we met Abhiram,Bhoomika,Rishav and Jayresh.
Unlike me and Subbu these people have contributed a lot to Mozilla and know what they are talking about. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So I grabbed the oppurtunity I had and started learning as much as I could from them.I really have to appreciate them for their patience and kindness.It was a 2 hour session about everything I needed to know to contribute to Firefox and the amount of knowledge I gained was substantial.So I guess it would be safe to say that my contributions to Mozilla will also be in a larger scale from now on.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="Mozilla"></category><category term="firefox"></category><category term="fsa"></category><category term="MozCoffee"></category></entry><entry><title>My road to becoming a firefox student ambassador</title><link href="/my-road-to-become-a-fsa.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2015-07-26T10:20:00+05:30</published><author><name>Lucifer</name></author><id>tag:,2015-07-26:my-road-to-become-a-fsa.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Mozilla Trichy Inaguration Meetup" src="" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So here I am a usual college kid with no clue about what I would like to persue or achieve in life.The Only two things I was proud of was joining an Engineering College and my intermediate skills in playing games.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Was I the only one ? Or are there a lot of kids out there like me who thought playing games and chatting online made you a good computer user or even at certain instances a "Pro" in computer usage.So this the part which turned my life upside down for the rest of time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It was on July 24,2015 That I got a call from one of my friends from the NGO I was on. He told me that there was going to be a meetup in TRICHY conducted by THE "Mozilla!".Obviously a common guy like me with no expertise in the field of Contribution the Community Projects would freak out and would want to attend the meeting.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here's the catch,Two days before his call was when I got a serious Swelling in my mouth due to infection and my lips were in the size of a piece of Orange.As all teenagers would do I started a mini-war in my head on whether or not I should go to this meetup.Obviously we would finally seek an elder's advice which will obviously destroy all hopes we had about going to the meetup.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That's when I found out how much I wanted to go there!,So I called my friend who picked me up on his bike and we went there. After the initial 10 minutes of ice-breaking, I was in full swing. I was good at debating but I didn't know I had this much passion for understanding and contribution to Open Software Communities.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I got to meet Vigneshwer who is a Mozilla rep who was travelling all around,gathering contributors all around the Southern part of TamilNadu.My Friend Makilan was there as well,He is part of the Mozilla Tanjore Community and last but not least the "Lil dude" Subbu was there. Initially we were supposed to start contibuting to firefox and spread the word out that we are here to support users if and when they needed help.So I took it upon myself to start working my way up as a good contributor and this is how my journey as a Firefox Student Ambassador began. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I feel like it was by mere coincidence that I got into Mozilla as a Firefox Student Ambassador but in the end is there any such thing called coincidence ? &lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="Mozilla"></category><category term="firefox"></category><category term="fsa"></category></entry></feed>